Register of the Charles E. McLure papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles E. McLure papers
1983-1985
99017
Hoover Institution Archives
24 manuscript boxes (9.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, working papers, and printed matter relating to American taxation policy during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan and especially to worldwide unitary taxation proposals.
McLure, Charles E.
Box 1-22
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Charles E. McLure, Jr. was born in Sierra Blanca, Texas on April 14, 1940. He received degrees in economics from the University of Kansas and Princeton University. He attended the University of Kansas for a Bachelor’s degree from 1958 to 1962. He then attended Princeton for both his Master’s and Doctoral degrees between 1962 and 1966. After a few years of teaching at Rice University, McLure served as the Vice President of the National Bureau of Economic Research from 1977 to 1981. In 1983, he became Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Treasury for Tax Analysis. McLure was responsible for developing the Treasury Department’s proposals to President Ronald Reagan for income tax reform. This work would be the basis for the Tax Reform Act of 1986. He was also Staff Director of the Working Group on Worldwide Unitary Taxation. At the end of his term as Deputy Assistant in 1985, he received the Treasury Department’s Exceptional Service Award. McLure has written extensively about tax reform and taxation, and has served as a consultant to various U.S. governmental agencies and international organizations. He received the Daniel Holland Medal from the National Tax Association in 2004.
McLure is currently a senior fellow at the Hoover Institution specializing in the economics of tax policy.
Scope and Content of Collection
Comprised of correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, working papers, and printed matter relating to American taxation policy during the Ronald Reagan administration. Materials are mostly focused on fundamental tax reform and worlwide unitary taxation proposals. There is a large amount of memoranda which is accompanied by supplementary materials related to tax reform. Original folder and binder titles have been retained when possible.
Reagan, Ronald.; United States. Dept. of the Treasury.; Taxation--United States.; Unitary taxation.; United States--Economic policy--1981-1993.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.
- Correspondence, 1983-1985
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence that is not directly related to fundamental tax reform or the debate on unitary taxes. Correspondence for persons other than the creator has been placed in a folder for others.
  - Letters sent, 1983-1985 (Text 1: 1)
  - Letters received, 1983-1985 (Text 1: 2)
  - For others, 1983-1985 (Text 1: 3)
- Memoranda, 1983-1985
  Treasury office memoranda organized by recepient. Some memoranda have additional materials attached.
  - Carlson, George, 1984 (Text 1: 4)
  - Chapoton, John, 1983 (Text 1: 5)
  - Chew, David, 1985 (Text 1: 6)
  - Deputy Secretary Darman, Richard G., 1985 (Text 1: 7)
  - Distribution, 1984-1985 (Text 1: 8)
  - Files, 1985 (Text 1: 9)
  - Gerardi, Gerry, 1984 (Text 1: 10)
  - Johnson, Manuel, 1984 (Text 1: 11)
  - McLure, Charles E. Jr., 1984-1985 (Text 1: 12)
  - Nestor, Skip, 1985 (Text 1: 13)
  - Neubig, Tom, 1985 (Text 1: 14)
  - Office of Tax Analysis Staff, 1984 (Text 1: 15)
  - Pearlman, Ronald A., 1984-1985 (Text 1: 16)
  - Pickford, David E., 1983 (Text 1: 17)
  - Rollyson, Mike, 1984-1985 (Text 1: 18)
  - Secretary Baker, James A., 1985 (Text 1: 19)
  - Secretary Regan, Donald T., 1983-1985 (Text 2: 1)
  - Thuronyi, Victor, 1984 (Text 2: 2)
  - Wilkins, John, 1984 (Text 2: 3)
- Worldwide Unitary Taxation Working Group, 1983-1985
  Materials related to the the Worldwide Unitary Taxation Working Group which was formed for the purpose of taxing multinational corporations. The creator's original folder and binder titles have been retained when possible.
  - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Text 2: 4-8)
  - Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Text 2: 9)
  - Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Text 3: 1-5)
  - Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Text 4: 1)
  - Worldwide combined reporting: A compilation of materials, November 1983 (Text 4: 2-5)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group volume 1, 1983 (Text 4: 6)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group volume 1., 1983 (Text 5: 1)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group volume 2, 1983 (Text 5: 2-4)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group volume 3, 1983 (Text 5: 5)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group volume 3, 1983 (Text 6: 1-2)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group volume 4, 1983 (Text 6: 3)
  - Initial meeting, 2 November 1983 (Text 6: 4)
  - Second meeting, 6 December 1983 (Text 6: 5)
  - Third meeting, 1 May 1984 (Text 6: 6)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group testimony, 29 November 1983 - 1 December 1983 (Text 6: 7-8)
  - Unitary Tax Working Group testimony, 29 November 1983 - 1 December 1983 (Text 7: 1-2)
  - Statements to the task force, 1983-1984 (Text 7: 3-4)
  - Organisation for Economic Co-Operation and Development, 1984 (Text 7: 5)
  - Briefing papers, 1984 (Text 7: 6)
  - Briefing material, 1 May 1984 (Text 7: 7)
  - Reports, 1984-1985 (Text 7: 8)
  - Task force report, 1 May 1984 (Text 8: 1)
  - Working Group report, 1984 (Text 8: 2-3)
  - Working papers, 1983-1985 (Text 8: 4-6)
  - Working papers, 1983-1985 (Text 9: 1-4)
  - Water's Edge file, 1983-1984 (Text 9: 5)
  - Notes, 1983-1985 (Text 9: 6)
  - Printed matter, 1983-1984 (Text 9: 7)
- Fundamental Tax Reform, 1983-1985
  Materials related to Fundamental Tax Reform. Creator's original folder and binder titles have been kept when possible.
  - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Text 10: 1)
  - Letters to the Treasury, 1983-1984 (Text 10: 2-5)
  - Fan mail, 1984-1985 (Text 10: 6)
  - Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Text 11: 1-6)
  - Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Text 12: 1-5)
  - Decision memos (Business), 1984 (Text 12: 6)
  - Decision memos (Business), 1984 (Text 13: 1-2)
  - Working papers, 1983-1985 (Text 13: 3-6)
  - Working papers, 1983-1985 (Text 14: 1)
  - Project outline, 1984 (Text 14: 2)
  - Tax reform issues, 1984-1985 (Text 14: 3)
  - Income tax issues (Business), 1984 (Text 14: 4-5)
  - Income tax issues (Personal), 1984 (Text 14: 6-7)
  - Subject list of questions and answers, 1984-1985 (Text 15: 1)
  - Aspects of Tax Policy: 1985 and Beyond, 1983 (Text 15: 2-3)
  - Tax reform topics (Modules), 1984 (Text 15: 4-6)
  - Administrative issues, 1984 (Text 16: 1-4)
  - Tax Reform for Fairness, Simplicity, and Economic Growth Volume 1, November 1984 (Text 16: 5-6)
  - Floppy disks, 1983-1985 (Text 17: 1-2)
    Floppy disks and accompanying index that contain documents related to Fundamental Tax Reform.
  - Notes, 1984 (Text 17: 3)
  - Fiscal Year 85 budget material presented at White House, January 1984 (Text 17: 4)
  - Treasury fact sheets, 1984 (Text 17: 5)
  - Fundamental Tax Reform 1984 (Text 18: 1-3)
  - Individual income taxes, 1984 (Text 18: 4-5)
  - Tables and figures, 1984-1985 (Text 18: 6)
  - Tables and figures, 1984-1985 (Text 19: 1)
  - Tax reform meetings volume 1, 1984-1985 (Text 19: 2-4)
  - Tax reform meetings volume 2, 1984-1985 (Text 19: 5-6)
  - Tax reform meetings volume 3, 1984-1985 (Text 20: 1-3)
  - Alcan Amicus Brief, 1985 (Text 20: 4)
  - Tax reform sections, 1985 (Text 20: 5-7)
  - T-II questions, answers and fact sheets, 1985 (Text 21: 1-2)
  - Talking points, circa 1985 (Text 21: 3)
  - Reform proposals, 1985 (Text 21: 4-8)
  - Fundamental Tax Reform 1985 (Text 22: 1-4)
  - Writings by others, 1985 (Text 22: 5-7)
  - Tax reform drafts, 1984-1985 (Text 23: 1-3)
  - Clippings and articles, 1984-1985 (Text 23: 4)
  - Printed matter, 1984-1985 (Text 23: 5)
  - Printed matter, 1984-1985 (Text 24: 1)
- Printed Matter, 1979-1986
  Clippings, press releases, and published material discussing tax reform.
  - General, 1982-1985 (Text 24: 2-3)
    A varity of published material related to taxation during the early 1980s. A bulk of the materials are comprised of informational packets and pamphlets.
  - Tax notes, 1979-1981 (Text 24: 4)
  - Clippings, 1983-1985 (Text 24: 5)
  - Treasury News, 1982-1986 (Text 24: 6-7)
  - Analysis of the Impacts of the President's Tax Proposal on Major Sectors of the Energy Industry, August 1985 (Text 24: 8)